<body xmlns:ws="http://www.xmlpl.org/website">
  <h1>What is XmlPL?</h1>
  <p>
    XmlPL is a programming language which provides built-in
    features for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xml">XML</a>
    processing integrated with a C-like syntax.
    Among these features are XML path expressions and XML
    statements.
  </p>

  <p>
    XmlPL grew out of frustration with the inefficiencies and over
    complicated nature of existing methods for XML manipulation such
    as <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSLT</a>, <a
    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/">XQuery</a>, and API
    approaches like <a href="http://www.w3.org/DOM/">DOM</a> and <a
    href="http://www.saxproject.org/">SAX</a>.  XmlPL overcomes many
    of the problems with these approaches by treating XML as a native
    data type, integrating path expressions with a C-like syntax and
    compiling rather than interpreting to create an intuitive and
    efficient XML processing language.
  </p>
 
  <p>
    If you know
    <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_programming_language">Java</a>,
    <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_programming_language">C</a> or
    <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%2B%2B">C++</a>
    and <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath">XPath</a>
    then XmlPL is very easy to learn.  Since XML is a native
    data type it can be processed more naturally and efficiently
    using XML path expressions and inline XML.
  </p>

  <p>
    XmlPL is not intended to be a general purpose
    language.  It does aim to be an efficient language for
    general purpose transformation, interpretation,
    generation and augmentation of XML data.  XmlPL may also
    be used as an interface between XML data and other
    programing languages.
  </p>

  <h1>Status</h1>
  <p>
    XmlPL is currently in the <b>alpha</b> release stage.  This means that
    there are some known bugs and likely some unknown bugs.  However, XmlPL has
    been in development and real world use since 2003.  I hope you will find
    it useful.
  </p>

  <p>
    If you run in to
    problems please email <ws:email address="bugs@xmlpl.org"/> with an
    explanation of your problem, the machine and operating system
    use are using, the XmlPL code you are compiling and any error messages
    you encounter.
  </p>

  <h1>Features</h1>
  <ul>
   <li>
     <a href="http://www.opensource.org/">Open-Source</a> software.
     <ws:link sec="gpl">GPL</ws:link> for free.
     <a href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/bsd-license.php">BSD</a>
     for a fee.
   </li>
   <li>Supports inline XML data</li>
   <li>Uses an XML path language, similar to XPath, integrated with a
     C like syntax</li>
   <li>Provides advanced features for XML stream manipulation</li>
   <li>Gives the developer control over XML DOM memory usage</li>
   <li>Garbage collected</li>
   <li>Compiles to C++ for high portability and fast execution</li>
   <li>Easily extended with libraries and native code blocks</li>
  </ul>
</body>
